Last year was a great year for lithium
supplementation as a huge nature study
released indicating that lithium has an
incredible capacity to defend against
multiple mechanisms of brain harm in
Alzheimer's disease. Then, when looking
at some of the clinical data, there were
some similar benefits discovered. But,
it turns out that this year lithium is
taking its hits.
A punch to the gut and a swift uppercut
has the lithium Alzheimer's angle
staggering.
>> [laughter]
>> That's because a Physionic Insider
brought to my attention an analysis that
put together all of the lithium and
Alzheimer's studies, and the results hit
like a George Foreman fist. So,
have we been duped about lithium and its
Alzheimer's benefits? Well, we'll
discuss all that detail that you need to
know, including why I've changed my mind
about lithium.
>> [clears throat]
>> This meta-analysis, this is an analysis
of multiple studies combined to try to
find an effect of an intervention, in
this case the element lithium,
on an outcome, in this case Alzheimer's
disease, a brain disease, released
recently. In said analysis, the
researchers put together all the
clinical studies in lithium and put the
data together for comparison shown here.
Now, we see the studies listed on the
left, a bunch of statistics that I won't
bog you down with, and most importantly
the visualized results of all the
studies in the green squares and lines.
If these tiny green squares and lines
move to the left of the vertical line,
that means that lithium reduces symptoms
of Alzheimer's disease compared to not
consuming lithium. However, a key point
is that if the lines touch the vertical
line, then the interpretation is that
there's no effect of lithium. More
clearly represented, the overall effect
all the studies together are shown at
the bottom in the black diamond. Same
rules apply though. So, generally
lithium does not seem to have an effect.
But, but
the newest study, yeah, there's one
study
in 2013 that indicates a benefit of
lithium, even if all the rest don't.
Unfortunately, when we apply what's
known as a risk of bias assessment to
the studies, this is a test to determine
which studies have higher risk of bias
due to a number of factors, this single
study stands out as the only study to
indicate high risk of bias. So, do we
really want to count on this one study,
or should we rely on the weight of the
entire analysis? Typically, the latter.
More data, the better. In fact, when we
remove that one study, we really
solidify that there's no effect of
lithium. So, the point I want you to
take home from this is that this
meta-analysis of six clinical trials
indicates no effect of lithium
supplementation against Alzheimer's
disease, in direct opposition of the
excitement of last year. The researchers
went out of their way to include data
from a few studies that had not
published yet and had finished
collecting their data. So, things are
looking pretty grim, but I've also
become a more distrusting of
meta-analyses over the years. You may
have seen this hierarchy where the
meta-analysis is on the top of the
pyramid as the most powerful evidence on
the topic. Now, in a perfect world that
typically is true because you have more
data to detect effects. However, in the
present world, it's not so simple
because it also matters the quality of
the data, the criteria used by the
researchers for including or excluding
studies from the meta-analysis, and much
more that I again won't bore you with.
The bottom line is though is that not
all meta-analyses are equal, and some
are frankly trash. That then raises this
question of how this one stacks up.
Although I knew everything that I just
mentioned for some time, I've taken an
especially critical lens recently by,
when possible, opening the individual
studies of the analysis. So, that's what
I did here. Again, if we pop this open
again and we open this Forlenza study as
one example, I can tell you that this
study actually showed a worsening of
cognitive performance while the lithium
group remained stable over 1 year. Now,
by the defined measures of the
meta-analysis, it's true that the
difference was quite small between the
lithium and the placebo group. But,
nonetheless, there technically was a
benefit of lithium that is simply lost
in the statistics of the meta-analysis.
But, don't let me convince you that this
is an isolated problem because if we
were to extend our definition of
cognitive improvement from a single
measure to include other assessments,
all of these studies show a beneficial
effect of lithium supplementation. In
addition, some of the studies that
showed no effect, like the Devananda
study,
Devanand Devanand study, and this Hampel
study were only 12 and 10 weeks
respectively. Now, there may be
treatments that are highly effective
that may work in just 10 weeks, but just
because a treatment isn't effective on a
multi-year disease in 10 weeks does not
automatically rule it out for being
effective overall. These critiques
aren't even to mention that the
researchers included this Forlenza
study, but failed to include this
Forlenza study, which lasted longer and
had more participants and also found a
benefit of lithium. There's some other
critiques that I could levy, but I'll
refrain. The point is this meta-analysis
has significant flaws that make the
conclusions weak. Still, a weak
meta-analysis does not necessarily mean
that lithium is that effective. So, if
we put the critiques aside, what can we
still say about lithium's effectiveness
in protecting us from Alzheimer's
disease?
You know, there's some additional
details like how lithium affects amyloid
clearance, different types of lithium,
and some less discussed results related
to Alzheimer's disease. I'm covering
that plus more in my expanded analysis.
It's included as a Physionic Insider. If
you're interested in access to all that
plus all of my other work in video,
written, and audio format, then check
out the Physionic Insiders. It's my
premium research platform and community.
If your interest beeth peaked, you can
check out the Insiders using the link in
the description. Plus, you get these
perks right here. Hope to see you there.
Well, if we turn to some of the newer,
larger trials and we look at the
long-term exposure over years to
lithium, and then measure the
progression from mild cognitive
impairment to the progression to
full-blown dementia,
we see some striking results. The dark
blue line is the lithium and the pale
blue line is the placebo, so no lithium.
And the lower the lines go, the more
people have progressed to dementia, of
which Alzheimer's disease is included.
This is a measure over several years as
well. Clearly, lithium provides
protection based on this clinical
dementia rating. But, these kinds of
results in longer trials are not unique.
And generally, the studies that show no
effect are quite short. But also, don't
let me paint a picture that there are no
lengthier studies that also don't show
an effect. I don't have access to some
of these studies because, well, they
aren't published yet or they're in
Japanese, and while I do understand
multiple languages, Japanese is not one
of them, and artificially artificial
intelligence has failed me. So,
is there room for lithium to still come
out as ineffective? Absolutely. I just
don't think that we should be relying on
incomplete or insensitive analyses as a
reason to eliminate lithium from
contention. I really think that we're
quite early in understanding lithium's
impact though. I still lean in favor
until better evidence indicates
otherwise. Still, some things have
changed for me. For example, dosing used
in the studies varies widely.
Previously, I mentioned trace doses of
lithium being effective. That's still
true. However, there are also studies
using much larger sums. So, effective
doses have been used anywhere from 300
micrograms per day of elemental lithium
to 600 milligrams per day of lithium
salt, like carbonate and sulfate. Ah,
the intricacies of research.
Fascinating, aren't they? If you'd like
more on how lithium actually causes this
protective effect for the brain, then
check out my initial analysis on the
topic right here. Thanks for stopping
by. I hope it proved informative. Catch
you in the next one. See you.